{
  "title": "Utah History - People",
  "path": "KnowledgeBowl/",
  "data": [
    {
      "questionType": "Drill and Kill",
      "question": "Governor",
      "items": [
        {
          "question": "Who was the first governor of the State of Utah?",
          "answer": "Heber Wells"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which governor served in the 1980s that had to solve flooding problems of the Salt Lake?",
          "answer": "Norman Bangerter"
        },
        {
          "question": "What non-Mormon governor did President Buchanan appoint over the Utah Territory.",
          "answer": "Alfred Cumming"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who is the current governor of the State of Utah?",
          "answer": "Gary Herbert"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who was Utah's 15th Governor?",
          "answer": "Olene Walker "
        },
        {
          "question": "Served as the 14th governor of Utah and resigned from office to serve in Federal Government offices?",
          "answer": "Michael Leavitt"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "questionType": "Drill and Kill",
      "question": "Utah Women",
      "items": [
        {
          "question": "Who was the first woman in the entire US to become a State Senator?",
          "answer": "Martha Cannon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who was the first elected Judge in Utah?",
          "answer": "Reva Beck Bosone"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who became the first school teacher in Salt Lake City after the pioneers arrived?",
          "answer": "Mary Jane Dilworth"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who was Utah's 15th Governor?",
          "answer": "Olene Walker "
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "questionType": "Drill and Kill",
      "question": "Native Americans",
      "items": [
        {
          "question": "Which Indian group is older the Anasazi or Fremont?",
          "answer": "Anasazi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which Indian group is older the Anasazi or Fremont?",
          "answer": "Anasazi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which Indian group used the atlatl?",
          "answer": "Anasazi"
        },
        {
          "question": "What group of Indians are known as the 'Ancient Ones?'",
          "answer": "Anasazi"
        },
        {
          "question": "What ancient group of Utah Indians are known for their petroglyphs?",
          "answer": "Fremont"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which Indian group left paintings and carvings in Utah?",
          "answer": "Fremont"
        },
        {
          "question": "What Indian tribe is the largest(5,000) in Utah?",
          "answer": "Navajo"
        },
        {
          "question": "What Indian tribe is the second largest(3,000) in Utah?",
          "answer": "Utes"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which Indian group hunted on horses?",
          "answer": "Utes"
        },
        {
          "question": "There are less than 100 of these Indians left in Utah",
          "answer": "Goshutes"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "questionType": "Drill and Kill",
      "question": "Native Americans",
      "items": [
        {
          "question": "Where did the Anasazi live?",
          "answer": "Cliffs or Caves"
        },
        {
          "question": "Where did the Fremont live?",
          "answer": "Abode Stone Homes"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "questionType": "Drill and Kill",
      "question": "Native Americans",
      "items": [
        {
          "question": "Which Chief tried to unite all native Americans to fight back to retain land and refuse to relocate?",
          "answer": "Chief Blackhawk"
        },
        {
          "question": "What was the name of the chief and his wife who were peaceful and intelligent diplomats who worked to resolve resettlement issues?",
          "answer": "Chief Ouray and his wife Chipeta"
        },
        {
          "question": "What Indian Chief peacefully negotiated land for his Shoshone people in Wyoming?",
          "answer": "Chief Washakie"
        },
        {
          "question": "Name two chiefs who converted to the LDS faith?",
          "answer": "Chief Kanosh and Chief Walker"
        },
        {
          "question": "What was the name of the Indian who was killed without a trial?",
          "answer": "Old Posey"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "questionType": "Drill and Kill",
      "question": "Dates",
      "items": [
        {
          "question": "When did the Fremont live in Utah? ",
          "answer": "900-1100 AD"
        },
        {
          "question": "In what year was Martha Cannon elected?",
          "answer": "1896"
        },
        {
          "question": "What year was Alfred Cumming appointed governor over the Utah Territory",
          "answer": "1859"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "questionType": "Drill and Kill",
      "question": "Definitions",
      "items": [
        {
          "question": "Who studies artifacts of people and their culture.",
          "answer": "Archaeologist"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who studies plant and animal remains.",
          "answer": "Paleontologist"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "questionType": "Drill and Kill",
      "question": "Ute Words",
      "items": [
        {
          "question": "What does the Ute word 'Kunni' mean?",
          "answer": "Horse"
        },
        {
          "question": "What does the Ute word 'Apats' mean?",
          "answer": "Boys"
        },
        {
          "question": "What does the Ute word 'Pigatas' mean?",
          "answer": "Little Fish"
        },
        {
          "question": "What does the Ute word 'Uinta' mean?",
          "answer": "Pine Land"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "questionType": "Drill and Kill",
      "question": "People",
      "items": [
        {
          "question": "Name the men who broke land speed records at Bonneville Salt Flats?",
          "answer": "Craig Breedlove, Abe Jenkins"
        },
        {
          "question": "Name the men that explored these rivers-The Green River and the Colorado River?",
          "answer": "Ashely, Powell"
        },
        {
          "question": "What explorers from Spain came to Utah looking for gold?",
          "answer": "Juan Maria rivera, Bernado Miera"
        },
        {
          "question": "Name explorers who were sent out by the US Government as soldier to make maps? ",
          "answer": "Bridger, Fremont, Powell"
        },
        {
          "question": "Spanish Fork Canyon connect Spanish Fork Utah to Price. Who traveled down this canyon while exploring Utah?",
          "answer": "Father Dominguez, Father Escalante"
        },
        {
          "question": "What explorers was looking for a new route to California through Utah?",
          "answer": "Father Dominguez, Father Escalante"
        },
        {
          "question": "'Crossings of the Fathers' along the Colorado River is named after who?",
          "answer": "Father Dominguez, Father Escalante"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who were the Spanish Padres who were the first to explore and write about Utah?",
          "answer": "Father Dominguez, Father Escalante"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "questionType": "Drill and Kill",
      "question": "Explorers",
      "items": [
        {
          "question": "Who lead a two year expedition to survey the Great Salt Lake?",
          "answer": "Howard Stansbury"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who explored the Green River",
          "answer": "Ashley"
        },
        {
          "question": "What one armed explorer made the first recorded trip down the Colorado River?",
          "answer": "John W. Powell"
        },
        {
          "question": "Flaming Gorge gets its name because of the sun on the red rocks. Who choose its name?",
          "answer": "John W. Powell"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who explored the Colorado River",
          "answer": "John W. Powell"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who are the Salt Flat of the western Great Salt Lake named after?",
          "answer": "Benjamin Bonneville"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who established Camp Douglas during the Civil War?",
          "answer": "Patrick E. Connor"
        },
        {
          "question": "Many Americans from the East Coast did not believe his stories about geysers in Yellowstone, Wyoming?",
          "answer": "Jim Bridger"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which mountain man discover the Great Salt Lake?",
          "answer": "Jim Bridger"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who was the first white man to visit the Great Salt Lake?",
          "answer": "Jim Bridger"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which government explorer was known as the 'Pathfinder'?",
          "answer": "John Fremont"
        },
        {
          "question": "Name an explorer that was send out the the US Government to make maps?",
          "answer": "John Fremont"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Bear River in Utah was explored by who?",
          "answer": "John Fremont"
        },
        {
          "question": "Name a mountain man who was a guide for John Fremont?",
          "answer": "Kit Carson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which mountain man had his ear ripped off by a bear and sewn back on by a friend?",
          "answer": "Jedediah Smith"
        },
        {
          "question": "What Bible reading Mountain Man is known as the greatest trapper-explorer in Utah?",
          "answer": "Jedediah Smith"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who was the explorer that was killed by Indians while surveying a railroad in central Utah?",
          "answer": "John Gunnison"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who studied Mormonism and reported positive things to the US Government?",
          "answer": "John Gunnison"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "questionType": "Drill and Kill",
      "question": "People",
      "items": [
        {
          "question": "Who was an early LDS church historian?",
          "answer": "B.H. Roberts"
        },
        {
          "question": "What LDS apostle also became a US Senator?",
          "answer": "Reed Smoot"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who in Utah sent the first telegraph message across the transcontinental telegraph line?",
          "answer": "Brigham Young"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who started what is now called the University of Utah in Salt Lake City?",
          "answer": "Brigham Young"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Hinckley Family was called by who to run Cove Fort, Utah",
          "answer": "Brigham Young"
        },
        {
          "question": "What was the name of the Mormon Tabernacle Choir Director who led from 1890 to 1916?",
          "answer": "Evan Stephens"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who assisted in designing and inventing a version of the modern odometer?",
          "answer": "Orson Pratt"
        },
        {
          "question": "Original member of the LDS church's Quorum of the Twelve?",
          "answer": "Orson Pratt"
        },
        {
          "question": "The first Prophet of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints?",
          "answer": "Joseph Smith"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "questionType": "Drill and Kill",
      "question": "Schools",
      "items": [
        {
          "question": "What was the name of the school started by Brigham Young in Provo?",
          "answer": "Brigham Young Academy"
        },
        {
          "question": "The University of Utah was previously called?",
          "answer": "University of Desert"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "questionType": "Drill and Kill",
      "question": "People",
      "items": [
        {
          "question": "Who led the Utah Symphony for many years and has a symphony hall named after him?",
          "answer": "Maurice Abravanel"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who found the largest dinosaur skeleton in the world?",
          "answer": "Dr. James Jenson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who led the US troops to establish a non-Mormon Government?",
          "answer": "Sidney Johnston"
        },
        {
          "question": "What famous car racer later became Mayor of Salt Lake City?",
          "answer": "Ab Jenkins"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who owned the Mormon Meteor?",
          "answer": "Ab Jenkins"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who is known as the Candy Bomber?",
          "answer": "Gail Halvorsen"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who bought the Salt Lake Tribune?",
          "answer": "Thomas Kearns"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who started the Fur Trappers Rendezvous?",
          "answer": "William Ashley"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "questionType": "Drill and Kill",
      "question": "People",
      "items": [
        {
          "question": "Who is Ogden, Utah named after",
          "answer": "Peter Skene Ogden"
        },
        {
          "question": "Provo, Utah is named after who?",
          "answer": "Etienne Provost"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who found the Bingham Copper Mine?",
          "answer": "Patrick Connor"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who established Fort Douglas and the Bingham Copper mine for Utah",
          "answer": "Patrick Connor"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "questionType": "Drill and Kill",
      "question": "People",
      "items": [
        {
          "question": "Name three explorers and the Utah rivers they explored?",
          "answer": "Fremont-Bear River; Ashley-Green River; Powell-Colorado River"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is the name of the spear throwing devise used by the Anasazi?",
          "answer": "Atlatl"
        },
        {
          "question": "A hunting tool used by the Anasazi is called?",
          "answer": "Atlatl"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}